Challenges to Free and Open Source Software
Prev  |   |  Next

Challenges to Free and Open Source Software

Software Patents
Copyright Infringement Laws
Licence Proliferation

Having to reimplement software due to incompatible licences

Copyright Assignment
Open Source Software Becoming Unmaintained
The “Removing sesame seeds” syndrome
Hostility from Members of the Community to Newcomers

Open source appears to be very successful, but as of 2011, there are some challenges that threaten to undermine it. While it is not probable that open-source software will completely die as a result, these challenges should nonetheless be taken into consideration. This section aims to list them.

Software Patents

Software patents are patents that cover algorithms used inside a computer program, and prevent a competitor from implementing it as well. Software patents can often be very generic, can be trivial to think about, can have some prior art upon acceptance, and their cost of issuing and cost of patent litigation are beyond the reach of most small-time open-source developers.

There have been many cases of patent litigation in the past by large companies, and there are some companies which consist entirely of lawyers who get hold of some patents and sue large companies for infringement, hoping to make some money. The English Wikipedia has coverage of the software patent debate

Copyright Infringement Laws

Some recent anti-copyright infringement laws such as the notorious Digital Millenium Copyright Act (or “DMCA” for short.) or the more recent ACTA, can be used to prohibit the distribution of some open source software, such as those that can be used to break the copyright-protection measures of some content providers.

The Electronic Frontier Foundation has published a document titled “Unintended Consequences: Twelve Years under the DMCA”, which contains a list of “cases where the anti-circumvention provisions of the DMCA have been invoked not against pirates, but against consumers, scientists, and legitimate competitors”.

Licence Proliferation

Having to reimplement software due to incompatible licences

Many source code licences were approved as free software or open source by either the Free Software Foundation or the Open Source Initiative. The problem is that if one encounters a software package that is distributed under one of these licences, they will have to become aware of this licence’s peculiar restrictions. Furthermore, it will be difficult to tell whether it will be compatible with code under a different licence.

As a result, there’s the problem of licence proliferation.

Having to reimplement software due to incompatible licences

Some licences are known to be incompatible with one another: the GPL version 2 with the GPL version 3 or LGPL version 3, the GPL version 2 with the Apache License, all versions of the GPL with the original BSD licence, and many other non-GPL-version-2 or non-GPL-version-3 compatible licences. As a result, often, a program that is open-source is still unusable, and will have to be reimplemented.

Furthermore, some projects or organisations may consider the software under Strong copyleft licences, or even weak copyleft licences to be too restrictive, and will instead opt to rewrite it. Here are some cases of open source code being made unusable due to problems with their licensing:

For example, the Free Software Foundation now started the GNU PDF project that is licensed under the GPL version 3, because all the other Free software PDF projects are GPL version 2 only. So because the GPL was used, the same problem need to be solved twice.

Another case where it happened was this story of an the Inkscape set operations patch:

Once before, someone had contributed a patch to add boolean operations, but that patch relied on a polygon clipping library provided under an incompatible license. There’s little more frustrating than having a solution in hand, only to be hamstrung by legal problems. Even though it was an important feature for us, we regretfully postponed development of it into the distant future on our roadmap and proceeded with other work.

Furthermore, the OpenBSD project are now re-implementing a lot of software that is only available as GPL or similar licences, under BSD-style licences, due to OpenBSD’s more pedantic licensing policy.

The GNU Project had to start working on develop the LGPLed GnuTLS because the licence of the also open-source OpenSSL library was not compatible with its GPLv2 and GPLv3 licences.

Reimplementing source code from scratch due to licence incompatibility is unfortunate, because open source developers have much more productive tasks to accomplish in their precious time. As a result, several open-source developers have opinionated that one should use a simple, non-copyleft and GPL-compatible licence, such as the MIT/X11 licence for all original source code, to encourage its reusability.

In an O’Reilly Media interview with him, back in 2005, Eric Raymond (who wrote the “Cathedral and the Bazaar” and spearheaded the Open Source Initiative organisation) has voiced the opinion that “We don’t need the GPL any more” and that people should avoid using that licence for new projects. Naturally, some people still disagree.

Copyright Assignment

Some projects done by companies, or other individuals, require copyright assignment on the part of their contributors, so the copyrights will remain under the same copyright owners, who may then be able to relicense their code under different terms. Many people have been reluctant to contribute to projects that require such copyright assignment, because they would like to keep their own copyrights. As a result, this undermines the Bazaar model of development and the atmosphere of community in general.

Copyright assignment is a complete non-issue with projects licensed under permissive licences (a.k.a BSD-styled ones), whose licences allow the copyright owners, or every other party, to sublicense such a project.

Open Source Software Becoming Unmaintained

There is a risk that open-source packages will become unmaintained, or spin-off a non-open-source version that will be more actively maintained. This is often seen as the risk of BSD-style licensed software, but it is not completely absent with GPLed one (see the story of the Nessus Vulnerability scanner). Even if the licence is a copyleft one, then there’s a risk of the originators of the programs stopping to update them, and no one stepping up to maintain them instead.

This problem is not specific to the FOSS world, because proprietary software also has become under-maintained or discontinued, but naturally the problem still exists.

The “Removing sesame seeds” syndrome

Joel on Software describes a situation of eliminating sesame seeds:

In one of Gerald Weinberg’s books, probably The Secrets of Consulting, there’s the apocryphal story of the giant multinational hamburger chain where some bright MBA figured out that eliminating just three sesame seeds from a sesame-seed bun would be completely unnoticeable by anyone yet would save the company $126,000 per year. So they do it, and time passes, and another bushy-tailed MBA comes along, and does another study, and concludes that removing another five sesame seeds wouldn’t hurt either, and would save even more money, and so on and so forth, every year or two, the new management trainee looking for ways to save money proposes removing a sesame seed or two, until eventually, they’re shipping hamburger buns with exactly three sesame seeds artfully arranged in a triangle, and nobody buys their hamburgers any more.

Such a situation may occur with open-source software or free content resources, where people gradually eliminate features or text, or introduce more bugs until the software is too unusable. A prime example for such case is the so-called ”Deletionism” in Wikipedia and other collaborative online wikis, where people gradually remove pages or parts thereof that they do not like.

Another bad aspect of that is driving away the contributors who donated these features, who feel demotivated by such an attitude.

Hostility from Members of the Community to Newcomers

Many people in the open-source community are known for their hostility towards people whom they don’t like. I voiced some criticism of the “usability” of the Perl Online World for Newcomers, and there are similar sentiments about problems in treating people in the “HOWTO Encourage Women in Linux” document. I’ve also witnessed how one very important open-source project, which I was involved in, stagnated, because its developers were incredibly rude on their on-line forums and scared away most potential contributors.

Such hostility may be detrimental to a project’s success or the success of the open-source community in general.

Prev  |   |  Next
Myths about Open Source and Other Issues  | Home |  Where I Stand

Other Criteria of Open Source Software
Prev  |   |  Next

Other Criteria of Open Source Software

GPL Compatibility
Copyleft
Open Source vs. Sourceware

GPL Compatibility

Making a program free is not necessarily enough to make it compatible with the GNU GPL licence. The GPL makes some restrictions regarding which licences it can link against, and some otherwise free software is not compatible with them. Examples for incompatible licences are the Mozilla Public License, the Qt Public License, and even the original BSD licence. It is advisable that, whenever possible, a developer or vendor should choose a licence that is compatible with the GPL, because otherwise there may be problems integrating his code with GPLed one or using both a GPL and a non-GPL compatible library. (I am not a lawyer, so I cannot conclusively say when it is legal or not).

Mozilla is an example for a large project that started out with its custom (albeit now relatively common), non-GPL compatible licence, and recently adopted a triple licence of the Mozilla Public License, the GNU General Public License, and the GNU Lesser General Public License in order to make it compatible with the GPL and to standardise its integrability. The Qt library whose commercial vendor and originator is Troll Tech Inc., also had adopted the GPL as well as its own Qt Public License, to relieve the various legal problems that KDE (a desktop system for UNIXes which is based on it) faced when using GPL code.

One relatively recent issue with the GNU General Public Licence had been the formation of Version 3 of both the GPL and the LGPL, which made programs that were only version 2 of the GPL (and not a later version) incompatible with those of the GPL version 3 or even the LGPL version 3. While some programs has been relicensed or sublicensed under version 3 of the GNU licences, a lot of software packages out there are stuck at being version 2 without an option for a later version, which make them mutually incompatible with the formerly licensed packages. Such FOSS packages include a large amount of the code of the Linux kernel, as well as Ghostscript and xpdf, which are commonly used for rendering the PostScript and PDF standards for ready-to-print-documents.

Copyleft

The copyleft definition

Copyleft means that a derived work of a copyleft software, that are not used for internal or personal use, must include the source code and released under the same terms of the original work. Copyleft is common in many licences including the GPL, the Lesser General Public License, the QPL, etc.

Many licences are not Copyleft - most notably the various BSD licences and MIT/X11 licences. Software released under such licences can be derived into a proprietary software product by a third party, and often have been.

Open Source vs. Sourceware

Not any software application that is accompanied by its source is open source, albeit many people who are new to the term would be tempted to think that. It is possible to write non-open-source software while accompanying it with the source.

Examples for such cases are:

The Microsoft Visual C++ Run-Time Library and the Microsoft Foundation Classes (MFC), that are accompanied with their source.

xv - a popular shareware image viewer and manipulator for X-Windows that has been distributed with its source code. Note: it is no longer actively maintained, and its developer can no longer be actively reached, and so its use is no longer recommended.

qmail - a popular mail server whose source code was available and can be deployed free of charge, but its licensing terms specified that it is illegal to distribute modified binaries or sources (at least outside the organization) This is enough to make it non-open-source, but it still had been a very popular program. More recently, the source of qmail, and several related programs by the same author, were made public domain, which now makes it open-source software.

None of these packages qualify as free software, but they are all accompanied with the source. There are many others around. A quick search on the Freecode directory of UNIX software will find many such packages.

In order for a program to be open-source it needs to be free of various restrictions as specified in the open-source definition. To be free software as well, it must be also free of some other restrictions. [5]

I believe the term open-source is a bit dangerous in this regard. Then again, free software may not automatically be associated with freedom and liberty, so it isn’t perfect either. But I guess finding a description that accurately describes it in a short space is not very possible, so these terms will have to do.

[5] In a query given by an Israeli Member of the parliament in the past, to an Israeli Defence Force (IDF) representative about whether all the software used by the Israeli military is open-source, the latter interpreted open-source software as software that the IDF has access to its source. This is an even more radical deviation from the correct meaning.

Prev  |   |  Next
Difference between “Open Source” and “Free Software”.  | Home |  Myths about Open Source and Other Issues

Meaning of the terms
Prev  |   |  Next

Meaning of the terms

According to the Free Software Definition free software must fulfil 4 freedoms:

The freedom to run the program, for any purpose

The freedom to study how the program works, and adapt it to your needs. Access to the source code is a precondition for this.

The freedom to redistribute copies so you can help your neighbour

The freedom to improve the program, and release your improvements to the public, so that the whole community benefits . Access to the source code is a precondition for this.

The Open Source definition is similar, but some licences can qualify as open-source and not as free software. This is usually not an issue, because the majority of open source software out there is free as well. Moreover, lately most of the companies and people who have phrased their own software licences, have tried to also get the Free Software Foundation to approve their licences as free software in their eyes.

Despite common belief, selling free/open-source software is perfectly legitimate. In fact, one can charge as much as he pleases for it. Nevertheless, most free software is distributed for free or for very cheaply on the Internet and other mediums. This is due to the fact that its freely distributable nature does not give way much to sale value, so there usually is no point in attempting to mandate a charge for selling it.

Another common misconception is that it sometimes cannot be modified or customised for internal use. In fact, all free software (but not all open source software), can. Only when you wish to distribute it (free of charge or commercially), you may have to distribute your changes (depending on the licence - not all open-source licences require that). The use of open source software to process proprietary content or be processed by non-open-source programs is also, always available. Thus, an open-source C compiler can be used to compile the code of proprietary programs, such as the Oracle database server.

Prev  |   |  Next
Software Licences and “Proprietary” Software  | Home |  History

Myths about Open Source and Other Issues
Prev  |   |  Next

Myths about Open Source and Other Issues

Sharing software huh? Isn’t it a bit like Communism?
The “Programmers Will be out of Work” because of Free Software Myth
Other Myths about Linux and Open Source Software

Sharing software huh? Isn’t it a bit like Communism?

This analogy is not new but very deceptive. First of all, there’s nothing anti-Capitalistic about sharing something voluntarily. While in a Capitalistic country, goods are generally sold and have to be paid for, people can voluntarily dedicate their time and money for any cause they wish, possibly altruistic. Communism in fact forces the sharing of all good, including physical ones that take time and money to manufacture each unit of.

Secondly, because manufacturing and distributing a unit of software costs practically nothing, it is not necessary that it will be sold. While the development cost can be very large, a developer of the software will not be encumbered by it being used by a million people instead of a thousand.

Furthermore, by making a software package open-source and keeping it so, it is possible to gain other economical and psychological advantages: you’ll make sure it is maintained, gain feedback and admiration of others, and may be able to eventually receive input and contributions from the outside. Distributing software as commercial proprietary packages does not automatically yield good advantages and it takes a lot of time and money to make it usable as well. Such a vendor is actually risking that his software will work at all, and not be out-competed by something better.

This analogy was rejected and treated in a semi-jokily manner by most people who did not oppose Capitalism as a whole. A true understanding of why open-source does not contradict the liberal ideals of Capitalism and Individualism originated from Eric Raymond’s “Homesteading the Noosphere” and “The Magic Cauldron”, which are a very good read anyway you look at it.

The facts themselves do not give way to it either. The free software movement is almost entirely limited to liberal Capitalistic countries, which are free enough to allow unrestricted programming and distribution of software to prosper. Furthermore, I cannot name a single prominent figure who is Socialist or Communist, or otherwise entirely anti-Capitalistic (albeit some may hold certain views of this kind). Lastly, open source or some open source software was recently endorsed by many IT and non-IT businesses who greatly benefit from it, including some vendors of proprietary software.

Finally, even assuming that free and open source software or partly-free-and-open cultural works (e.g: the various Creative Commons licences) have some elements of Communism or Socialism, does it really matter? After all, we enjoy the fruits of the many people who contributed to open source, the Wikipedias and other Wikimedia projects and various other free or mostly free works of culture and code, which would probably not have happened without them being free. As a result, even if open-source is indeed communistic or socialistic, it is nevertheless “good for the people” so to speak and should not be discouraged.

All of that put aside, it is clear that copyright laws do not and must not prevent people from applying not-fully-restrictive (nicknamed “All Rights Reserved”) licences to their original works, so eventually there will be enough people who out of either desiring to “help their neighbour” and/or out of motives that have more an aspect of a rational self-interest and without being forced to do so against their will, will be willing to release their works under open or semi-open licences.

The “Programmers Will be out of Work” because of Free Software Myth

It is unlikely that assuming Open Source becomes the dominant paradigm, it will imply that programmers will “starve to death”. As Eric Raymond notes in the Magic Cauldron, the vast majority of software applications out there are one without a sale value: be it software that large organization like banks, insurance companies or militaries use to power their critical systems, customizations, scripts or code used within smaller organizations (Microsoft Access customizations, spreadsheets’ formulae and macros, Perl or shell scripts), embedded software whose source code is not released to the public, software that powers web-sites and was not released to the public, etc.

The majority of programmers out there are employed for developing such code, whose codebase dwarfs that of the marketplace software that includes all commercial and open-source software put together.

In due times, packages are developed and become available that makes some tasks that were once hard to do internally almost straightforward to set up and run. Nevertheless, these packages still require a clueful person to operate, diagnose problems, communicate with the vendor or developer and manage the configuration. For example, a complete computer beginner will probably not know what to do with a spreadsheet program (such as Microsoft Excel) without thoroughly studying it. Afterwards, it becomes a very useful tool.

Even if programmers do become out of job as a result of free software, then it will not necessarily a bad thing. It means that it solved problems that otherwise required extra hands, and so those programmers can be allocated for something else entirely that is more productive.

Other Myths about Linux and Open Source Software

One can very often hear many myths or generally accepted “truths” about open source software and Linux, some of which negative and other positive. Examples include:

1. Open source software is less secure than software whose source code is not revealed, because people can find bugs at it by looking at the code.

2. Open source software is more secure than closed-source software because more people can review the code and discover bugs in it.

3. Linux is harder to use than Windows.

4. Linux is not compatible with Windows.

5. Open source gives way to forking more easily.

And many others. The Linux Myth Dispeller attempted to answer some of these, with a focus on negative myths. Myth #1 is completely false as bugs can still be found by analysing the disassembly of the machine code. Also often such bugs are found by accident due to a certain valid use of the software) There were many closed-source packages out there in which many bugs have already been discovered. (like Microsoft Outlook, Microsoft IIS or Microsoft Internet Explorer). Some of these already became widely exploited a long time before a vendor patch was made available.

Myth #2 has a grain of truth in it. However, some open source packages nevertheless had very poor security records out of poor programming practices. Some closed-source offerings, on the other hand, have a very good security record. In most packages, security bugs occurred due to sloppy programming practice, or lack of auditing of the code. They can be mostly avoided whether or not the package’s source code is available to the public.

Myth #5 is not entirely true. While it is possible to fork a piece of open-source software, most packages have not been actually forked. Eric Raymond covers the customs that relate to forking a package in “Homesteading the Noosphere”, and Rick Moen explains why when major packages forked, it was not necessarily a bad thing in his “Fear of Forking essay”.

Moreover, many times proprietary software was forked as well. There are many flavours of System V UNIX out there, and there used to be many more. Microsoft released three different lines of Windows flavours with two or more simultaneously, and has many localised versions. (Which are many times incompatible with one another.)

Prev  |   |  Next
Other Criteria of Open Source Software  | Home |  Challenges to Free and Open Source Software

Where I Stand
Prev  |   |  Next

Where I Stand

It is customary in documents of this kind to convey the personal opinion of the author in this case. This document will not be an exception.

I am a user, developer and advocate of free and open-source software. However, I do not think that proprietary software is inherently immoral or destructive. I know some vendors of such software abuse their customers. However, I generally see them as suppliers of goods, which took a lot of time to develop, and which they perfectly naturally wish to sell for money.

The fact that open-source developers develop similar goods and distribute them for no cost or little cost, under a less restrictive open-source licence, does not invalidate this fact. I agree with most of what Eric Raymond said in the “Cathedral and the Bazaar” series, part of which is that proprietary software is problematic. However, I think that a world dominated by free software (which I hope to see soon) can exhibit some proprietary software without it having a generally harmful effect on the computer world at large.

I do not hate Microsoft, just think that their systems are much inferior to GNU/Linux, which I like better. I still use Windows when I find it appropriate, or when I need to. (I’m not an “I only use free software” kind of guy). I realise the superiority of Linux may have stemmed from the fact it is free software, but otherwise don’t use it only because it is free software. I just like to work with it better.

I don’t see Microsoft or other suppliers of proprietary software as enemies of the free software movement. I expect that people will continue to buy some proprietary software even after Linux and free software take over, assuming they do. I think Microsoft will eventually port their software to Linux if it gains enough market share. While they may lose the revenue generated from selling Windows and providing various services for it, I don’t think they will disappear entirely. And they may be able to find different revenue streams.

Open-source, however, can change the rules of the game, and I believe it will. In a world dominated by open-source, proprietary vendors must realise that they need to supply their customers with quality software, listen to what they say and act upon it, and constantly try to keep it above the open-source competition. There is no point in hiding the details of the Specs or protocols, and completely hiding the source code is not as important as many of them now think. If Microsoft survives in a Linux environment, we will see a much less abusive Microsoft.

My general ideology used to be a variation of “in for free beer”. Use, code, and be guiltless and happy. A recent encounter with a free for some uses proprietary software whose licence changed and I became unable to use it any longer, slightly modified it. In the future, I’ll be more careful in relying upon proprietary software, because it may become inaccessible to me, but otherwise still don’t hold the vendors of it as immoral. I still use some not-entirely-free software because I like it and am used to it or it gets the job done.

My stance regarding the war between the term “open source” and “free software” is that I use either one when I find it appropriate, and am not fanatical to either term. It depends on the context of using it, who I speak to, what I wish to imply, what sounds right, or the first thing that pops out of my head. I usually prefer saying “Linux” over “GNU/Linux” because it is shorter, and more snappy and people will understand what I talk about. I do sometimes resort to “GNU/Linux”, but not very often, and use the term a “GNU system” even more.

The fact I don’t stick to either open-source or free software, stems from the fact that I respect both the Free Software Foundation, and the Open Source Institute, and believe that the free software movement and the open source movement is pretty much one and the same. I also like both terms.

I don’t normally refer to Linux as “GNU/Linux” despite the fact that a large and integral part of it is derived from the GNU project, for marketing reasons. GNU/Linux is longer than Linux and does not add more information, just a lot of pseudo-ideology. Add that to the fact that many people will pronounce it “djee-enn-you-slash-Linux”, when they first see it, and you’ll get something that makes a very bad marketing name. Here’s a nice quote from Linus Torvalds on why “Linux” is superior to “386BSD” (a 90’s BSD clone that was free software as well):

  |

> > Other than the fact Linux has a cool name, could someone explain why I
> > should use Linux over BSD?
>
> No.  That’s it.  The cool name, that is.  We worked very hard on
> creating a name that would appeal to the majority of people, and it
> certainly paid off: thousands of people are using linux just to be able
> to say “OS/2? Hah.  I’ve got Linux.  What a cool name”.  386BSD made the
> mistake of putting a lot of numbers and weird abbreviations into the
> name, and is scaring away a lot of people just because it sounds too
> technical.

|
  | --Linus Torvalds

Well, the name “GNU/Linux” is a step in the wrong direction in this regard.

As a developer, I try to use permissive licences (usually the MIT/X11 licence), for software packages I develop and distribute. I don’t mind people making a derived code proprietary much less integrating it inside proprietary products. If the original code, which I modify or derive from, is distributed under a different licence, I respect the original licence, whatever it may be.

I used to think that some systems were critical enough to justify GPLing or LGPLing them. My opinion of all that changed after the entire mess caused by the enactment of the GPL version 3 and the LGPL version 3, which are mutually incompatible with the previously released version 2 of the GPL. I now believe that even if we distaste proprietary software, then copyleft licences such as the GPL or the LGPL are not worth the trouble and cause more harm than good. There is a lot of open-source code out there under permissive licences, and they don’t seem to suffer a lot from it.

Prev  |   |  Next
Challenges to Free and Open Source Software  | Home |  Links and References